<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Blog Name</title>
  <subtitle>Blog subtitle</subtitle>
  <id>http://blog.url.com/</id>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/"/>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2015-11-16T16:01:00-08:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Blog Author</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>How to beat writer's block using Slack</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/writers-block-slack/"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/writers-block-slack/</id>
    <published>2015-11-16T16:01:00-08:00</published>
    <updated>2015-11-18T11:35:19-08:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I counted just now, and apparently I've written about 15,000 words in the last three weeks. About 1/3 of a novel, going by the Nanowrimo convention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To clarify: I'm not doing Nanowrimo, this happened mostly by accident, and it is not normal for me to write so much. Writing is hard for me, generally, but these 15,000 words were easy. I'm actually pretty giddy about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To back up: like most of my peers, I've had A Blogging Goal since forever. It's an accepted truism in Silicon Valley that everyone who wants to be anyone should write – that even if it took you 20 years to get good and build up an audience, a good blog is so valuable that you ought to start on that right away. And like most people who want to write, I struggle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've been told I'm a good writer, actually. When I worked at Meteor, I wrote a lot for the blog and mailing list. One of my early posts – Why web beginners should start with Meteor – was [bragging statistic], and apparently inspired people to do drastic things like quit their job to learn to code. Back in college, I wrote some fanfiction, one of which has 154 reviews saying things like ["example"]. To this day, [X years later], I still get about one email notification a day saying someone has left me "kudos" on one of my stories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is: getting myself to write has historically been a laborious process involving a lot of procrastination, self-flagellation, accountability systems, locking myself in a room with the WiFi off and phone on airplane mode, pomodoros, goal-alignment meditation, and all kinds of other willpower-consuming attempts to impose discipline onto a brain that dives headlong toward the nearest source of internet fuckery and self-distraction whenever I ask it: "….sooo, shall we write today?" Even when it was my full-time job to write for Meteor, it took so much effort and willpower to have a good writing day, that I could only manage it about once a week, maybe two or three times if I was feeling cheerful and getting plenty of sleep and one of the posts was allowed to be formulaic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My main problem is in the rough-drafting phase, the "don't think, just write" early bit that is so critical if you want to be not just good, but prolific. I have premature editing syndrome like it's a disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So whence these 15,000 words in 3 weeks?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-thingy-in-a-nutshell"&gt;The thingy in a nutshell&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here it is: &lt;strong&gt;Do your rough drafting in a Slack chat channel instead of in a document.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That's it. It sounds a bit too-simple and anticlimatic when written down, but "I accidentally 15,000 words" crosses the threshhold where perhaps I am On To Something and should share it anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My personal slack channel wasn't originally conceived of as a writing aid – I figured I would mostly use it as a place to write down my goals for the day, or an inbox for interesting links and random todos that wandered across my attention. But it's turned out to be the perfect place to ramble stream-of-consciousness style about whatever I'm thinking about, which is what rough-drafting is all about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="the-how-to"&gt;The how-to&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) &lt;em&gt;Set up a Slack organization with a few trusted friends.&lt;/em&gt; These should be people that you like and find easy to talk to, people with whom you feel safe sharing half-baked thoughts. In my case, my roommates and I happened to have a house Slack organization. We had set it up back when we moved in together, just to chat and banter and keep on the same page about house things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) &lt;em&gt;Create a personal channel and invite your friends.&lt;/em&gt; I created a personal channel called #alice-, with its channel purpose set to: "Alice talks to herself, and maybe to you!"&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) &lt;em&gt;Write liberally about whatever's on your mind.&lt;/em&gt; Think out loud. Ramble. This space is all yours; you can write as much as you want without imposing on anyone, and other people can read it (if they want to) at their own pace. Keep it casual – you're just talking to yourself, after all. And not everything you write has to be Deep Thoughts and Future Blog Posts. Funny incidents and pictures from your day are A-OK too. Just share what's going on with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="why-it-seems-to-work"&gt;Why it seems to work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing in a slack channel somehow bypasses the part of my brain that makes "just writing" hard. It's not a Blog Post, or a thing to be Published – it's just me putting some thoughts down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somehow, email and chat falls into a different, easier category of writing. Words flow more easily when I'm looking at a chat input box or a Gmail compose window, compared to staring at a blank paper or text editor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With chat in particular, the medium encourages you to write just a little at a time, and it prevents you from easily going back and editing something you just wrote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems like a super cool hack. The writing itself is the most important part when you're getting started – more important than the medium or platform. If you write more easily in the form of chats or emails, you should take advantage of that, and give yourself permission to feel good about the writing you do in this format. It's "real" writing. It counts. And if it something interesting happens to come out of your chat ramblings, you can always package it up&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and if something interesting comes out, I can always package it up into a "proper" blog post if I want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;once you have the thoughts in words, however rough, the rest is relatively easy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to write fairly regularly on the CFAR alumni mailing list, and sometimes people would really like something I wrote and urge me to put it up somewhere so they could more easily share it with friends&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;btw, I really like what Joanna has done, publishing pieces of writing just as Facebook posts&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that's very much in the same spirit&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;anyway, inspired by this phenomenon, I registered alicedash.com just now&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a place to put my thoughts and writings in a more accessible format, when something interesting comes out of #alice- or similar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and named after this channel, to embody the spirit of ease and informality and flow that I experience here&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;thank you all for being my little rubber ducks :simple_smile: there's a kind of quiet, passive-listening quality to slack, that makes it really easy to talk&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the channel purpose says "Alice talks to herself, and maybe to you!" it really does feel like that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;"Alice talks to herself"… there's a kind of safe privacy here, like talking to your secret diary&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;"and maybe to you!"… but a kind of pointfulness and purpose that a diary lacks&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;anyway, I'd like to have a blog up at alicedash.com by end of Friday&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;please do hold me to that :simple_smile&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id="why-slack-in-particular"&gt;Why Slack in particular?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id="so-everything-is-easy-now-right"&gt;So everything is easy now, right?!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I woke up super early with my mind excitedly racing; couldn't fall back asleep&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;decided to get up and do something with my energy, after trying unsuccessfully to go back to sleep for an hour&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;so, like aray and joannabresee, I have a blogging goal&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find it super easy to put my thoughts down when I'm typing in this channel&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I generally consider myself to be a pretty good writer, but I have difficulty finishing drafts sometimes, and I'm not always good at "just writing" without overediting&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;at least when it comes to Blog Posts&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;things to be Published&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;but I've found that when I'm writing in the context of a chat, or an email, it somehow bypasses the part of my brain that makes "just writing" hard&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still edit, sometimes quite extensively (if it's an email)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;but the words just flow when I'm staring at a chat box or gmail compose window, instead of a blank text editor&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;this seems like a super cool hack. I think the writing itself is the most important part, more important than the medium or platform&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;so if I write more easily in chat or emails, I should take advantage of that, and allow myself to view this sort of writing as "real" writing, and feel good about it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and if something interesting comes out, I can always package it up into a "proper" blog post if I want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;once you have the thoughts in words, however rough, the rest is relatively easy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to write fairly regularly on the CFAR alumni mailing list, and sometimes people would really like something I wrote and urge me to put it up somewhere so they could more easily share it with friends&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;btw, I really like what Joanna has done, publishing pieces of writing just as Facebook posts&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that's very much in the same spirit&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;anyway, inspired by this phenomenon, I registered alicedash.com just now&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a place to put my thoughts and writings in a more accessible format, when something interesting comes out of #alice- or similar&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and named after this channel, to embody the spirit of ease and informality and flow that I experience here&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;thank you all for being my little rubber ducks :simple_smile: there's a kind of quiet, passive-listening quality to slack, that makes it really easy to talk&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;the channel purpose says "Alice talks to herself, and maybe to you!" it really does feel like that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;"Alice talks to herself"… there's a kind of safe privacy here, like talking to your secret diary&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;"and maybe to you!"… but a kind of pointfulness and purpose that a diary lacks&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;anyway, I'd like to have a blog up at alicedash.com by end of Friday&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;please do hold me to that :simple_smile&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
